Manschinger, Kurt and Grete Hartwig; Papers ger025
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Greta Hartwig Manschinger and Kurt Manschinger (Ashley Vernon) Papers
1896-1986
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger025
15.72 cubic ft.
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, opera librettos, songs, short stories, novels, sketches, and critical reviews. It also has personal family papers of Kurt (Ashley Vernon) and Greta Hartwig Manschinger, paintings and writings by and other records from Greta's sister Mela Hartwig and her husband Robert Spira, audio recordings, scores, and sheet music, as well as audio recordings of performances.
Biographical History
Greta Hartwig was born on April 19, 1899 in Vienna, at the time the capital of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. She was the daughter of Theodor Hartwig (born Theodor Herzl, later changed to differentiate himself from the famous Zionist), a noted German philosopher and advocate for free-thinking, and younger sister to Mela Hartwig, a well-known artist and author. Raised in a musical family, Greta was attracted to all forms of performing arts, her wide range of talents leading her to create the "One Woman Shows" that she became known for.
Dr. Kurt Manschinger, also known by the nom de plume Ashley Vernon, was born in 1902 in a Viennese suburb. A precocious youth with a talent for music, Kurt was schooled by the famous Austrian composer Anton von Webern during his teenage years. Eventually, Kurt would receive his doctorate in musicology from the University of Vienna in 1926. After establishing himself as a figure in the Austrian theater scene, Kurt would meet Greta as the starring actress in one of his plays.
Fiercely critical of fascism, Greta and Kurt were forced to flee their home country of Austria after its annexation by Nazi Germany in March 1938. First, the two fled to nearby Prague, where an inability to perform led to Greta's first foray into a writing career. Later, when the Hitler regime completed its annexation of Czechoslovakia, Greta and Kurt were forced to relocate to London in May 1939 where they helped found the anti-fascist literary cabaret "The Lantern", which hosted many of their fellow emigres who were fled the ever-rising violence of the Third Reich. The next year, the two would relocate for the final time, this time to New York City, and begin to re-establish themselves as mainstays in their respective artistic endeavors.
It was in America that the two found the most critical and commercial acclaim, with Greta successfully tutoring several students into prominent roles in film, stage, and television, while Kurt began to write operas. The most famous of these, "The Barber of New York", quickly became a critical and commercial success, being nominated for the Pulitzer Prize in 1954. In appreciation of their newfound home, both Greta and Kurt would become naturalized American citizens in April 1946.
Kurt died at home in 1968 while performing at his piano for a group of friends. Greta, never fully recovered from the loss of her husband, and passed away in April 1971 on vacation in Florida. Mela Hartwig Spira died in London in 1967, her husband Robert following just days later.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains biographical materials, correspondence and a significant amount of artistic output (manuscripts, opera librettos, songs, short stories, novels, sketches, sheet music, scores, audio recordins, and related critical reviews) from Greta Hartwig and Kurt Manschinger. The collection also contains original scholarly and artistic works by Greta's sister, Mela Hartwig Spira, and her father, Theodor Hartiwig, and materials related to Mela's husband, Robert Spira.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged into three series and all are arranged alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
The majority of items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Wilbur S. Broms, executor for the estates of Greta Hartwig Manschinger and Kurt Manschinger on 1983 March 13. Additional materials were added to the collection by Wilbur Broms in the later 1980s and by Martin Broms, son of Wilbur Broms on 2006 April 6.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Hartwig, Greta, 1899-1971; Vernon, Ashley; Hartwig, Mela; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Women authors; Music; Literature; Art; Correspondence; Scores; Painting; Novels; open reel audiotapes; Photographs
- Biographical, 1896-1971; 1; 2.58 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains biographical information regarding Greta Hartwig and Kurt Manschinger, including important legal documents surrounding their flight from Austria, brief autobiographical profiles of Kurt and Greta, Greta's daily calendars, legal materials related to Mela Hartwig and Robert Spira, plus many photographs of the Manschinger and Hartwig families.
  - Biographial Data on Kurt Manschinger and Greta Hartwig, 1955-1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Caricature Addressed to Greta and Kurt, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Daily Calendar of Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Greta Hartwig Bio and Story, 1956-1957; 1967-1968; 1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Greta Hartwig Manschinger Obituaries, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kurt Manschinger and Greta Hartwig Naturalization, 1946 April (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kurt Manschinger Obituary, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Legal Docs (Immigration, Marriage, Death,etc.), 1929-1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photo Negatives, 1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photograph Album, Grete Hartwig, 1926; 1929-1930; Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Photograph Album, Kurt Hartwig, Undated (Oversize 1)
    Photographs of Greta and Mela's younger brother brother who died in 1924.
  - Photograph Album, "To the Memory of the Kaiser Mountains"/"Zur Erinnerung an das Kaisergebirge", 1912 Summer (Oversize 2)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1910-1958; Undated (Oversize 2)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1930-1931; Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1931-1940; Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1932-1935; 1937 (Oversize 1)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1941-1944; 1946-1950; Undated (Oversize 2)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1950-1952 (Oversize 1)
  - Photograph Album, Untitled, 1950-1951; 1953-1965; 1967-1970 (Oversize 2)
  - Photographs, Greta and Kurt Manschinger, 1937; 1948; 1950; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, Greta Hartwig Manschinger, 1916; 1968-1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Josef Felder, 1932; 1965-1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Katherine Hartwig, 1896; 1907-1913; 1918-1920; 1931-1935; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Knitwits, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Kurt Manschinger, 1914; 1917-1918; 1920; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Kurt Manschinger, 1947-1948; 1951; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, Mela and Robert Spira, 1918; 1921; 1930; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, Raoul and Helga Manschinger, 1931; 1953; 1961-1962; 1965-1966; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Theodor Hartwig, 1914; 1923; 1946; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, Unidentified Groups, 1905-1909; 1921-1922; 1935-1939; 1955-1966; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Unidentified Individuals, 1925-1926; 1962; 1967; 1969; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, Without People, 1937; 1958-1959; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Prints, 1968; Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Robert and Mela Hartwig Spira, Final Statement on their Estate, 1965-1971; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Robert Spira, Obituary, 1967 June (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1916-1986; 2; 2.2 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series consists of correspondence by Kurt and/or Greta Hartwig Manschinger to various friends, family members, and working associates. Much of the material concerns their attempts to develop their business endeavors in the United States, with several personal letters to family members still in Europe included as well. In addition, there are letters concerning the Manschinger estate and legacy from executor Wilbur Broms dated after Kurt and Greta's deaths.
  - After Dinner Opera Company - Richard Flussel, 1953-1958; 1963-1965; 1968; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Antonia Viktora, 1946-1947; 1949; 1954-1955; 1960-1962; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Associated Music Publishers, 1948; 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Correspondence (German), 1931; 1937; 1956; 1976; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Aufbau", 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Austrian Institute And Forum, 1965; 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Austrian Labor Committee, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bagatelle, 1959; 1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barber of New York, 1942; 1969-1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Belwin-Mills Publishing Corp., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bertha Hartwigova, 1950; 1953-1959; 1958-1959; 1971; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bertha Klausner, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bertha Skribany, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Broms Family, 1956-1957; 1960-1962; 1964-1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bruno Walter, 1937; 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Business Letters, 1961; 1963; 1966-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cards and Letters to Greta Hartwig: Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cerny Verlag, 1946-1952; 1954-1955; 1959; 1966-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Congratulations Letters, 1947; 1951-1953; 1958; 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Copyright Registration, 1944; 1947-1950; 1952-1959; 1966-1967; 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence to Greta and Kurt Manschingers, 1963-1965; 1968-1973; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: To "Piper" (Merge), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Crossed Out Copies of Letters Mailed Having Important Material, 1944; 1965-1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dance, 1950; 1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - De Koven, 1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Delkas/Leeds, 1944-1948; 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dr. Adolf Rott, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dorrance and Company, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dorrance (Merge), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - EB. Marks Music Group, 1941; 1975; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Edith Harowitz and Martin, 1957; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Elkan-Vogel Co., 1942-1944; 1947-1952; 1955-1958; 1961-1963; 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dr. Emil Oprecht, 1941; 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Eric Juhn, 1968; Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Erika Korpnerls MS Man in Her Life, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - (Dr.) Ernst Oto Kuster, 1939; 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Ernst Schwager, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Erwin Tinter, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Europaischer Verlag, 1967-1975; Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Eva TiedeMann, 1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - La Farce Du Contre Bandier, 1956-1957; Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Freundschaft" Magazine, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Fritz Brainin, 1963-1964; 1969-1971; 1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - George Harnish, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Gertrud Magaziner, 1959; 1964; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, American Council for Emigres, 1949; 1954-1955; 1965; 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, Cupid and Psyche, 1946; 1960-1961; 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, Re: T.H. Hartwig, 1946; 1949-1950; Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, Turnau Opera Players, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Greta Hartwig, Employment, 1946; 1948-1959; 1965-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, Employment (Miscellaneous Companion, Non Professional), 1951; 1961; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, Household Miscellaneous, 1951; 1954; 1958 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Greta Hartwig Correspondence, Vocal Exercises, Wilbur Broms and Joseph Felder, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Greta Hartwig Letter to Sandra, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Greta Hartwig - Letters To and From (In German), 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Greta Hartwig Librettos - Correspondence, Etc. Poems, 1952; 1954; 1962; 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Greta Hartwig Manschinger to ASCAP, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Greta Hartwig Manschinger to Friends Following Accident, 1965 July (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Greta Hartwig Memorial, Undated; 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Greta Hartwig Miscellaneous Letters In German and English, Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Greta Hartwig To Kurt Manschinger, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Greta Hartwig to Theodor Hartwig and Bertha Hartwig, 1920; 1977; Undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Greta Keller, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Dr. Gustav Senger (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Hans Moldenhaver, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Hans Stern, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Dr. Hans T. Wohlmuth, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Harry Zohn, 1966-1967; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Hetha Manschinger, 1954; 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Horowitz, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Hymische Suite, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "Hymische Suite" (Merge), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Irene Paulson, 1959; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Irma Tyson, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Jirina Vaneckova, 1941; 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Josef Fedler, 1967; 1969-1970; 1974 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Josef Luitpold - Stern, 1943-1956; 1960-1961; 1964-1966; 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Karl Adler, 1967; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Karl Freytag, 1943-1954; 1956; 1958; 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Kate Hartwig, 1945; 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Knitwits, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Kurt Manschinger and Greta Manschinger Molden Haver, 1964-1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Kurt Manschinger Copying/ Auto Graphing, 1944; 1947; 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, American Committee For Christian Refugees, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Cupid and Psyche (See Also Theo. Presser), 1956-1957; 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Grand Slam (See Also Theo. Presser Co.), 1955-1957; 1967-1968; 1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Madame Dorette, 1934; 1942-1946; 1950; 1968; 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Mille-Fleurs, 1950; 1955-1956; 1959-1961; 1965; 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Miscellaneous Works, Performances, Etc, 1939; 1966; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Mrs. McWilliams and The Lightening, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Quintet, 1942; 1946-1949; 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Sinfonieta, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Songs, 1949-1950; 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Symphony in 2 MVTS, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kurt Manschinger Correspondence, Triumph of Punch (See Also Theo. Presser), 1954-1961; 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kurt Manschinger Family, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Kurt Tueholsky Kreis, 1963; 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Laughter And Tears From Shakespeare, 1962-1966; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters From Joan Wilson, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters of Condolence, 1968-1969; 1971-1972; 1974; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Library of Congress, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Libretto - Fragments - Unfinished Heartis Trump, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Librettos - Original, 1954; 1957 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Librettos (Translation) - Gluck's The Reformed Drunkard, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Librettos (Translation) - Haydn's The Apothecary, 1957; 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Librettos (Translation) - Mozart's Bastien and Bastienne, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Librettos (Translation) - Pergolesi's Tracollo, The Thief and Correspondence and Agreements With The After Dinner Opera and Flusser, 1954; Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Librettos (Translation) - Salieri's Little Harlequinade, 1952-1953; 1955; 1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lili Kaerber, 1943; 1953-1960; 1971; 1981-1982; Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Liner Notes, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Literary Cabret", 1957; 1960; 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Literary Works - Collaborators, 1941-1942; 1944-1946; 1948-1951; 1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Literay Works - General, 1946-1950; 1953-1954; 1957-1958; 1966-1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Little Hartiquinade, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Louisville Orchestra, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Lu Hsing", 1943-1948; 1950-1954; 1967-1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Manschinger Memorial Concert, 1972; 1971-1972; 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Manschinger Music - General, 1963; 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Maria Hans, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Maje Korst, 1968; 1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Mela Hartwig Spira, 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mela Hartwig Spira, 1955-1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Menstrel", 1949; 1954; 1967 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - (Merge) Rudolf Cerny and Cerny Verlag, 1968; 1970 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Mimi Grossberg, 1965; 1967; 1971 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1931; 1961-1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Music Print Corporation, 1958; Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Nelly, 1947; 1952 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - New Haven Opera, 1971; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - New York College of Music, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Olga Kirchneiner, 1941; 1945-1952 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Oskar Maria Graf, 1949; 1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Otto Kuester, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Performance - Miscellaneous, 1956; 1958; 1969 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Personal Letters, 1916; 1967-1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Philsophical Letters From Greta Hartwig's Father To Kurt Manschinger and Letters to Kurt From a Friend in Austria Describing The Social and Economic Situation in Austria (1947 - 1948), 1946-1948; 1952; Undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Picard Agency - Zurich, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "PiperL", 1949 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Press Release From Wilbur S. Broms, 1972; Undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Press Music Corp., 1957-1958; 1959-1961; 1963; 1968; 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Professor Hartwig - Greta's Father, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Raoul Manschinger, 1947-1952; 1962; 1964-1965; Undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Rendevous in Manhattan Contract, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "Rhapsody for Oboe", 1946-1947; 1958; Undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Robert Spira, 1948; 1950; 1964-1965; 1954; 1956 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Ronald Wellington Jones, 1968-1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Rose Auslander, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Rudolf Packness (Uncle), 1941; 1949 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - SESAC Inc. - Richard Flusser, Undated; 1953 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Sinfonietta, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Society for German-American Studies, 1970-1972; Undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Songs - Translation, 1952; 1968 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Special Material: Wiener Klein - Kunstplatte (Plans For Recording Project), 1970-1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Staackmann Verlag, 1928; 1930 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Students and Personal Correspondence, 1968-1970; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Symphony in 2 Movements, 1968; 1971; 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Triumph of Punch, 1954; 1961; 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vaneckova, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Voice of America, 1949; 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Who is Who in Music?", 1953-1954; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Wilbur Broms to Moldenhauer, 1971-1980; 1982; Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Artistic Works, 1916-1984; 3; 10.94 cubic ft.
  This series includes original works created by Kurt and Greta Hartwig Manschinger, as well as Greta's sister Mela Hartwig Spira and their father Theodore Hartwig. Among the works are short stories, novels, playlets, librettos, operas, choral arrangements, scholarly articles, paintings, drawings, and recorded musical performances. Included with the works themselves are programs and reviews for various performances that the Manschingers were associated with. Materials related to Greta's teaching are also present, including correspondence, programs, and reviews from former students and institutions that she taught at.
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including the National Anthem, Undated (Reel 51)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including What Now My Love, Undated (Reel 52)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Once Upon A Time, Undated (Reel 53)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Married, Undated (Reel 54)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Something Wonderful, Undated (Reel 55)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Jeunes Fillettes, Undated (Reel 62)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Song from the Depth, Undated (Reel 63)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Du Lieber Heiland, Undated (Reel 64)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including If You Go Away, Undated (Reel 65)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including He Loves Me, Undated (Reel 66)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Havah Nagilah, Undated (Reel 67)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Put on Your Sunday, Undated (Reel 68)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Taking a Chance, Undated (Reel 69)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Open a New Window, Undated (Reel 70)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including The Move, Undated (Reel 71)
  - Accompaniment for Greta, Including Hotshki Votshki, Undated (Reel 72)
  - Aesop's Fables Dramatized By Greta Hartwig, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Vasil, 1966; 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles About Mela Hartwig Spira, 1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles By Greta Hartwig for German Newspapers, 1963; 1935; 1937; 1950; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Associates: Edith Lenar Horowitz, 1951; 1955; 1959-1960; 1968-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Associates: Fritz Brainin, 1969-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Associates: Irene Paulsen, 1969-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Associates: Lili Korber (Grave), 1953; 1956; 1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Associates: Mimi Grossberg, 1958; 1964-1965; 1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Associates: Wilbur Broms, 1959-1961; 1963; 1965; 1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Assorted Programs, 1967; 1969-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Assorted Works, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - An Audition, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Betty Voorhees, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Blue Flower, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bob Hart, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bolschewiki, Menschewiki, Wutki (30 Songs, No.3), 1930; Undated (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - Brunhilda Ruiz, 1963; 1965-1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Carol Joy, 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Children: Bernardo The King, A Play for Children, 1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Children: Playlets, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Children: Pretty - Children's Story, 1948; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)